Bookstore Press Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Bookstore Press Records.
undated, 1967-1976.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Bookstore Press.
5.3 linear feet.
MSS19970027
Small press publisher (1971-1976) of poetry, children's books, and cookbooks located in Lenox, MA. The press was owned by Gerald Hausman. Authors and illustrators published by the press include Ruth Krauss, Paul Metcalf, David Kheridan, Sam Cornish and Maurice Sendak.
History
The Bookstore Press began publishing in 1971. The first book published was a collection of poetry by its founder, Gerald Hausman, titled New Marlboro Stage. Working out of Lenox, Massachusetts, Hausman, assisted by his wife Lorry and David Silverstein, published poetry, children's books and cookbooks. Among the children's authors published by the Press were Ruth Krauss, Crockett Johnson and Sami Cornish. Illustrators included Maurice Sendak and Jeanne Johns. Poets included David Kherdian, Paul Metcalf and David Cumberland among others. The Press ceased publication in 1976.
Scope and Content
The collection is primarily comprised of correspondence to Gerald Hausman, his wife, Lorry, and David Silverstein regarding submissions to and publications of the press. Correspondents are authors and illustrators published by the Press, along with a few others not directly associated with the Press including reviewers, authors, and small press publishers. Principal correspondents include David Kheridan, Ruth Krauss, Gerard Malanga, Paul Metcalf and Aram Saroyan. Much of the correspondence is personal in nature. No copies of out-going letters are included. A few manuscripts of books, typescripts and photostats of poems and other ephemeral materials are also present in addition to books, pamphlets and periodicals from the Press and other small press publishers. Also included are audiotapes of readings and interviews by Halsey Davis, Gerald Hausman, Bill DeVri, Ruth Krauss and Gerard Malanga.
Separated from the collection: All books pamphlets and periodicals have been transferred to the appropriate collections of Archives & Special Collections and are listed below.
Atkinson, Ron. Looking for My Name.
Atkinson, Ron, ed. Our Place.
Brock, Alice May. My Life as a Restaurant.
Brock, Ray. Go Fly a Kite.
Canner, Mark and Collins, Dana, eds. The Second Berkshire Anthology.
Cornish, Samuel James. “Grandmother's Pictures.” Fire Exit Magazine 3.
Cornish, Samuel James. Grandmother's Pictures. 2 copies
Cornish, Samuel James. Short Beers.
Cornish, Samuel James. Your Hand in Mine.
Cumberland, David. Death and Justice Frescoes. 2 copies
Cumberland, David. Love and Its Loves.
Girodias, Maurice. Between Books: A Manner of Press Release.
Hausman, Gerard. Berkshire Anthology.
Hausman, Gerard. Beth: The Little Girl of Pine Knoll.
Hausman, Gerard. Circle Meadow. 3 copies
Hausman, Gerard. New Marlboro Stage. 3 copies
Hogrogian, Nonny. Handmade Secret Hiding Places.
Kherdian, David. Any Day of Your Life. 2 copies
Krauss, Ruth. The Carrot Seed.
Krauss, Ruth. Everything Under a Mushroom.
Krauss, Ruth. If Only.
Krauss, Ruth. I'll Be You and You Be Me.
Krauss, Ruth. Monkey Day.
Krauss, Ruth. “News.”; Locus Solus 2.
Krauss, Ruth. Somebody Else's Nut Tree, and Other Tales from Children. 2 copies
Krauss, Ruth. This Breast Gothic.
Krauss, Ruth. Under 13.
Krauss, Ruth. Under Twenty. 2 copies
Kunhardt, Dorothy. Pudding is Nice.
Lippman, Peter. From Here to There.
Malanga, Gerard. The Blue Book.
Malanga, Gerard. Light/Licht.
Malanga, Gerard. Nine Poems for Cesar Vallejo.
Malanga, Gerard. Poetry on Film.
Malanga, Gerard. Prelude to International Velvet Debutante.
Malanga, Gerard. Six Portraits.
Malanga, Gerard. Ten Poems for Ten Poets.
Malanga, Gerard. 3 Poems for Bendetta Barzini.
Malanga, Gerard. 22.
Metcalf, Paul. Blood of the Lamb.
Metcalf, Paul. Will West. 2 copies
Saroyan, Aram. The Beatles.
Saroyan, Aram. The Bolinas Book.
Saroyan, Aram. The Library at Night.
Saroyan, Aram. Marijuana and Me.
Saroyan, Aram. The Rest.
Saroyan, Aram. The Street: An Autobiographical Novel.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( undated, 1967-1976 )
Series II: Audio Tapes ( undated, 1970 )
Series III: Display Materials ( undated )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of literary papers. See especailly, the papers of Ruth Krauss, David Kheridan, Aram Saroyan, Gerald Hausman, Cid Corman and Gerard Malanga and the Records of Cricket. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Hausman, Gerald—Correspondence.; Hausman, Lorry—Correspondence.; Silverstein, David—Correspondence.; Kherdian, David—Correspondence.; Krauss, Ruth—Correspondence.; Malanga, Gerard—Correspondence.; Metcalf, Paul C.—Correspondence.; Saroyan, Aram—Correspondence.; Authors and publishers—Massachusetts.; Editors—United States.; Authors, American.; Poets, American.; Publishers and publishing—Massachusetts.; Publishers and publishing—United States.; American literature—20th century.; Little presses—Massachusetts.; Cookery—Publishing—United States.; Children's literature—Publishing—United States.; Massachusetts—Business, industries, and trades—Publishing.; Lenox (Mass.)—Business, industries, and trades—Publishing.; Massachusetts—Cultural affairs—Literature.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Books.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Photographs.; Audio tapes.; Poems.; Interviews.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased in 1976.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1967-1976
  - Atkinson, Ron, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Berkshire Herald see Vibert
  - Bookstore Press see Hausman
  - Borland, Hal, 1968-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Brautigan, Richard, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Brock, Ray, 1975-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Burke Clifford, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Ciardi, John, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Corman, Cid, 1969-1970 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Cornish, Samuel James, 1973-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Cricket see Hyman
  - Davenport, Guy, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - DeVries, Peter, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Dustbooks see Fulton
  - Eberhart, Richard, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Edson, Russell, 1973-1974 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Freeway Press see Malanga
  - Fulton, Len, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Gibson, Bill, 1972-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Giligia Press see Kherdian
  - Henry, Marguerite, 1968 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Hillerman, Tony, undated (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Hyman, Trina Schart, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Johns, Jeanne, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Johnson, Crockett, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Kherdian, David, 1967-1971 (Box 1:, Folder 22-23)
  - Kinnell, Galway, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - Koller, James, 1971-1975 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
  - Krauss, Ruth, 1970-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 26-27)
  - Leisk, David Johnson see Johnson, Crockett
  - Lippman, Peter, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1972-1973 (Box 1:, Folder 29)
  - Malanga, Gerard, 1974-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
  - Malanga, Gerard, undated, 1973-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 31)
  - Meltzer, David, 1972 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
  - Metcalf, Paul, 1972-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
  - Minasian, Katchik, 1969 (Box 1:, Folder 34)
  - The New Yorker see DeVries
  - Rockwell, Molly (Mrs. Norman), 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 35)
  - Rothenberg, Jerome, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
  - Saroyan, Aram, 1973-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 37)
  - Saroyan, Aram, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 38)
  - Saroyan, Aram, undated (Box 1:, Folder 39)
  - Saroyan, Aram, undated (Box 1:, Folder 40)
  - Saturday Review see Ciardi
  - Sendak, Maurice, 1973 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
  - Smith, Kelly, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 42)
  - Snyder, Gary, 1975-1976 (Box 1:, Folder 43)
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1970 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
  - Vibert, Ed, 1974 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
  - Wakoski, Diane, 1971 (Box 1:, Folder 46)
  - Wilbur, Richard, 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
  - Wilentz, Ted (Theodore), 1975 (Box 1:, Folder 48)
- Series II: Audio Tapes, undated, 1970
  - Davis, Halsey—Poetry Reading, undated (Box 1:, Othertype Tape 1)
  - Hausman, Gerald—Poetry Reading, undated
  - Hausman, Gerald—High School reminiscences, undated (Box 1:, Othertype Tape 2)
  - Hausman, Gerald—Poetry Reading at Housatantic Valley High School, 1970 (Box 1:, Othertype Tape 3)
  - Krauss, Ruth—Interview by Valerie Sheehan, undated (Box 1:, Othertype Tape 4)
  - Malanga, Gerard—Interview by Hausman re Krauss, undated (Box 1:, Othertype Tape 5)
- Series III: Display Materials, undated
  - Cardboard display materials, undated (Oversize 2)